Jacquelyn A. Ottman Collection of J. Ottmann Lithographing Company 1880-1911 PR 281
New-York Historical Society
Jacquelyn A. Ottman Collection of J. Ottmann Lithographing Company
1880-1911
New-York Historical Society
Ottman, Jacquelyn A.
PR 281
0.5 Linear feet in 1 box.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Provenance
The collection was donated by Jacquelyn A. Ottman in January 2010 with additions in 2019.
Bibliography
J. Ottman Consulting, Inc. "J. Ottman Consulting Celebrates J. Ottmann Lithographing". New York, J. Ottman Consulting, 2009.
"Large Fire in Warren Street", New York Times. 17 Mar, 1882:8
Last, Jay T. The Color Explosion: Nineteenth-Century American Lithography. Santa Ana, CA: Hillcrest Press, 2005:112-113.
"Notable Manufacturers", King's Handbook of New York City. Ed., Moses King. Boston: Moses King, 1892:885.
Biographical Note
Jacob Ottmann (1849-1889) was born in Meisenheim, Prussia and immigrated to New York with his mother and seven brothers and sisters in 1863. Ottmann began his lithographic career in 1867 as a clerk at Ferdinand Mayer & Company, after deciding against joining his family's Fulton Market meat business. In 1874, Ottmann signed on as junior partner with the firm of Mayer and Merkel, located at 22-24 Church Street; the firm was then renamed Mayer, Merkel & Ottmann. In 1879 Mayer, Merkel & Ottmann moved to 21-25 Warren Street, which was also the business location of the firm's most renowned client, Puck magazine.
Puck was founded in 1871 in St. Louis by Josef Ferdinand Keppler, an Austrian-born cartoonist and caricaturist. Named for Puck, the impish character celebrated by Shakespeare in "A Midsummer Night's Dream", it began as a weekly humor magazine and was the first magazine in America to offer color illustrations. After the magazine's initial run in St. Louis as a single sheet proved unsuccessful, Keppler moved to New York City. In September 1876, the first Puck magazine was printed in New York City in German on the presses of Mayer, Merkel and Ottmann. An English version followed in March 1877.
The first issues were printed on a plain black press, followed by simple and then increasingly more complex multichromatics. Eventually, Puck evolved into a thirty-two page issue which sold for ten cents. Each issue contained a full-color political cartoon on the front cover and a color non-political cartoon or comic strip on the back cover. There was always a double-page centerfold, usually on a political topic. Inside, numerous black and white cartoons illustrated the humorous anecdotes, fiction, non-fiction, poetry, and editorials. In addition to co-publisher Keppler, the group of cartoonists included Dalyrymple, C.J. Taylor, F.M. Howarth, Fred Opper and J.S. Pughe. The last few pages contained ads.
In 1885, Mayer and Merkel retired from the firm and Ottmann took over the business, renaming it J. Ottmann Lithographing Company. That same year, Ottmann joined with the publishers of Puck magazine, Joseph Keppler and Adolph Schwarzmann, to commission construction of a new office building on Houston Street. By 1886, the Puck Building, today a New York City historic landmark, was ready for occupation. Ottmann died in November 1889. The J. Ottmann Lithographing Company continued in business until the first decade of the 20th century, after which it merged with the United States Printing and Lithographing Company. Jacquelyn A. Ottman is the great niece of Jacob Ottmann.
Scope and Content
The Jacquelyn A. Ottman Collection of J. Ottmann Lithographing Company contains items produced by the J. Ottmann Lithographing Company (and its predecessor Mayer, Merkel and Ottmann) between 1880-1911. The bulk of the collection is comprised of complete issues of, and tear sheets from, Puck magazine. Puck, founded in 1871 in St. Louis by Josef Ferdinand Keppler, began as a weekly humor publicaton and was the first magazine in America to offer color illustrations. Examples of these illustrations, including political cartoons, caricatures, and comic strips, can be found in Series I-III.
The collection also includes examples of the wide variety of other work produced by J. Ottmann Lithographing Company, including board games, paper doll kits, advertising cards, and postcards. The items in this collection items were gathered and preserved over the course of three decades by Ottmann's great-niece, Jacquelyn A. Ottman. The collection also includes a copy Jacquelyn A. Ottman's 2016 memoir, "Ottman and Company: One Daughter Remembers."
Many pieces in this collection were part of the exhibit, "J. Ottman Consulting Celebrates J. Ottmann Lithographing" at the Puck Building, September 14-24, 2009. More information on the exhibit and specific pieces in the collection can be found in the collection file, held in the Print Room.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 6 series by format:
Series I. German language magazines (full issues)
Series II. English language magazines (full issues)
Series III. Tear Sheets from Puck Magazine
Series IV. Toys and Games
Series V: Cards and Prints
Series VI: Publications
The material within each series is arranged chronologically.
Related Materials
The New-York Historical Society also holds The Joseph Keppler Cartoon Collection (PR 29) containing original lithographs by Keppler for Puck magazine.
Advertising cards.; Board games; Card games (game sets); Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Paper dolls; Periodicals.; Periodical covers; Photochroms.; Political cartoons -- United States.; Postcards.; Puck (English edition); Puck (German edition); Tear sheets.; Dalrymple, Louis, 1866-1905; Keppler, Joseph Ferdinand, 1838-1894. -- Pictorial works; Opper, Frederick Burr, 1857-1937; Ottmann, Jacob, 1849-1889; Pughe, J. S.; Taylor, Charles Jay, 1855-1929; J. Ottmann Lithographic Company
- Series I. German language Magazines (full issues), 1881-1896
  - Subseries I.A Puck, 1888-1896
    - Aug 8, V. 12, No. 48, 1888 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Aug 22, V. 12, No. 50, 1888 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Dec 12, V. 13, No. 14, 1888 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Oct 16, V. 14, No. 6, 1889 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Mar 25, V. 15, No. 29, 1891 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Nov 22, V. 18, No. 12, 1893 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Feb 19, V. 20, No. 25, 1896 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Subseries I.B Puck Illustrated, 1881-1884
    - Jan 19, V. 5, No. 18, 1881 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Aug 10, V. 5, No. 47, 1881 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Aug 31, V. 5, No. 50, 1881 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Dec 27, V. 7, No. 15, 1882 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - May 7, V. 8, No. 34, 1884; All cover cartoons by F. Opper. (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II. English language Magazines (full issues), 1883-1911
  - Subseries II.A: Puck, 1883-1911
    - Jan. 3, Vol. XII, No. 304, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Jan. 5, Vol. XX, No. 513, 1887 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Jan 16, Vol. XXIV, No. 619, 1889 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Jan 23, Vol.XXXVI, No. 933, 1895 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Feb 6, Vol. XXXVI, No.935, 1895 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Feb. 20, Vol. XXXVII, No. 937, 1895 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Jan 2, Vol. XLVIII, No. 1243, 1901 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Feb 6, Vol XLVIII, No. 1248, 1901 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Nov. 27, Vol. LXII, No. 1604, 1907 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Dec. 2, Vol. LXIV, No.1657, 1908 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
      Scope and Contents
      Cover reads "Christmas 1908."
    - Dec. 1, Vol. LXVI, No. 1709, 1909 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
      cover reads "Christmas 1909."
    - Sep. 20, Vol LXX, No. 1803, 1911 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Subseries II.B Puck's Library, 1897-1898
    - Jan, No.114, 1897 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Jul, No.132 (Cover only), 1898 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries II.C Puck's Monthly Magazine and Almanac, 1911 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Aug, No. 80, 1911 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
- Series III. Tear Sheets from Puck Magazine, 1880-1900
  Arrangement Note
  Where specific dates of tear sheets are unknown, items are arranged by printing company. Mayer Merkel & Ottmann Litho. 23-25 Warren St. indicate dates pre-1885. After this time, J. Ottmann moved the company to the Puck Building and formed J. Ottmann Lithographing Co.
  - Subseries III.A Front Covers, 1880-1900
    - Jul 21,Vol. VII, No. 176, 1880 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Sep 1, Vol VII, No.182, 1880 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Sep 22, Vol. VIII, No. 185, 1880 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Feb 2, Vol. VIII, No. 204, 1881 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Feb 28, Vol. XII, No. 312, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Nov 19, Vol. XVI, No. 402, 1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jan. 19, Vol. XX, No. 515, 1887 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jul 4, Vol. XXIII, No. 591, 1888 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jan 23, Vol. XXIV, No. 620, 1889 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Feb 6, Vol. XXIV, No. 622, 1889 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Feb 13, Vol. XXIV, No. 623, 1889 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Feb 20, Vol. XXIV, No. 624, 1889 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Feb 27, Vol. XXV, No. 625, 1889 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Mar 13, Vol XXV, No. 627, 1889 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Mar 20, Vol. XXV, No. 628, 1889 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Mar 27, Vol XXV, No. 629, 1889 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Feb 5, Vol. XXVI, No. 674, 1890 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jan 2, Vol. XXXVI, No. 930, 1895 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jun 6, Vol. XLVII, No. 1213, 1900 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - May 16, Vol. XLVII, No. 1210, 1900 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jun 27, Vol. XLVII, No. 1216, 1900 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jul 25, Vol. XLVII, No. 1220, 1900 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Aug 22, Vol. XLVIII No. 1224, 1900 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Subseries III.B Back Covers, circa 1880-1888
    - Mayer, Merkel & Ottmann Litho. 23-25 Warren St., New York, 1880-1885 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
      Cartoon captions include:
      "Spanish Courtesy"
      "Gathering Autumn Leaves"
      "Puck's Life of Garfield"
      "Through Murder to Salvation"
      "Great Political Excitement in Indiana - the Whole State on the Stump"
      "The Opposition Tabernacles"
    - J. Ottmann Lith. Puck Building, N.Y., 1886-1900 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
      "A Poor Outlook"
      "The Amazing Growth of the Pension Pig"
      "Busted!"
      "The Brave Old Bull-Fighter"
      "Times Have Changed"
      "Public Office is a 'Family Snap'"
      "The Regulation End of the Strike"
      "What Show Will They Have?"
      "Uncle Sam Sees What is Behind the Albany Ceiling Scandal"
      "An April Fool Joke on the New York Board of Aldermen"
      "Sure Cure!"
      "History Repeates Itself"
      Getting Rid of the Surplus"
      "The Latest Idol of 'The Grand Old Party of Moral Ideas'"
      "Too Much Shop"
      "Another Victory for 'Honest Labor'"
      "Not Wanted"
      "Our Doctors and Lawyers"
      "Our Patriot-Crank Abroad"
      "Our Household Patents"
      "When the Dime Museum Boom Bursts"
      "The Importance of a Beard - A Tale of Two Medical Students"
      "Nosegay's New Year Experiment"
  - Subseries III.C Centerfolds, 1880-1900
    - Mayer, Merkel & Ottmann Litho. 23-25 Warren St., New York, 1880-1885 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
      Captions for the cartoons include:
      "The Army-Worm"
      "Bankruptcy As a Popular Business"
      "The Social Treadmill-Fashion Keeps Her Bond-slaves at it All the Year Long"
    - J. Ottmann Lith. Puck Building, N.Y. (14), 1886-1900 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
      "High Protectionist Humbug vs. The Cold Truth"
      "Before the Tournament"
      "It's Not Hot Enough for Him Yet"
      "Quality Counts"
      "In the Arena For the Great Nomination Contest of 1892"
      "The Administration Guillotine"
      "Blaine and Boodle-the Kind of Cabinet That Suits The 'Greatest Living Statesman'"
      "The Minority Be D----D!"
      "The Chicago Platform Applied in St. Louis"
      "Declined With Thanks"
      "The Chinese Kopje;-Not So Easy As It Looked From A Distance"
      "A Hint From History"
      "Muzzling the Press"
      "One Reason in Four Tableaux. Why the 'Better Element' Never Happens to Get a Popular Vote in New York City"
  - Subseries III.D Miscellaneous, circa 1880-1890's
    - Puckograph (Mayer Merkel & Ottmann Litho. 23-25 Warren Street, New York), circa 1880 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    - Partial magazine with Centerfold (J. Ottmann Lith. Puck Building, N.Y.), 1895 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    - Cartoons - single page, circa 1884-1900 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
      "His Ambition is Larger Than His Mantle"
      "The Rapid-Growing Plant"
      "A Catch"
      "The Bunco Game in the Jungle"
      "The New Member of Monopoly Lodge Has Taken the 'First Degree'"
      "The Presidential Donkey-Party"
      "Union Against Union"
      "The Trailing Skirt; - Death Loves a Shining Mark"
- Series IV. Toys and Games, circa 1890-1907
  - Game of Peter Coddles, circa 1890 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - Game of Rex, 1900 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Teddy Bear Paper Doll Kit (2), circa 1907 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
- Series V. Cards and Prints, 1884-1910
  - Subseries V.A Advertising Cards, circa 1884-1893
    - Gold Coin Stoves and Gold Medal Ranges (Bussey & McLeod Stove Co.), circa 1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - unidentified [child with dog], circa 1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Mrs. Winslow's Soothing Syrup, 1888 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Smith & Anthony Stove Company, 1889 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Clark's Spool Cotton, circa 1890 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Estey Organ Co., circa 1890 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Hires' Rootbeer, circa 1890 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Franco American Food Co., circa 1890 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Phillips & Clark Andes Stove Company, circa 1890 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Spicers & Peckham Stove Founders, circa 1890 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Sterling Piano, circa 1890 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Waterbury Watch Co., circa 1890 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - New Home Sewing Machine Co., 1891 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Singer Manufacturing Company, 1892-1893 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - J. Ottmann Lithographing Company, 1893 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Plaza Hotel, New York, 1893 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Wheeler & Wilson Sewing Machines, 1893 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Subseries V.B Post Cards, 1901-1910
    - Novelty postcards by cartoonist R. F. Outcault, 1905 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Holiday greetings and miscellaneous postcards, 1901-1910 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Subseries V.C Miscellaneous Prints, 1888-1900
    - "Schuylkill River", circa 1900 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - General Edward F. Jones, 1888 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
- Series VI. Publications, 2016
  - "Ottman and Company: One Daughter Remembers," by Jacquelyn A. Ottman, 2016 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)